我们来谈谈双目视差。正如我之前提到的，这是一种技术
Let's talk some more about binocular disparity. As I mentioned before it’s a technique that's
通过动物非常普遍，它也是一种用于机器人的技术。
very widespread through animals and it's also a techniques that's used in robotics.
尝试理解双眼视差原理的一个好方法就是看看这个
A good way to try and understand the principle of binocular disparity is to look at this
非常老式的立体照片。这是一对相同场景的照片但是
very old-fashioned stereo photograph. It's a pair of photographs of the same scene but
每个图像都是从略微不同的视角拍摄的，这对应于
each image is being taken from a slightly different viewpoint and this corresponds to
我们的左眼和右眼的观点。
the viewpoint from our left eye and our right eye.
它相隔8到10厘米，它们会给你一个非常不同的
This is separated by that 8 to 10 centimetres and they give you a very slightly different
世界观。对这张立体照片的初步检查表明没有
view of the world. Initial inspection of this stereo photograph indicates that there's not
差别很大。如果我们放大这里的几个区域，我们会在左侧看到
much difference. If we zoom in on a couple of areas here, we see that in the left
手形图像，有相当大的差距，实际上右手图像没有间隙。
hand image, there's quite a gap and there's in fact no gap in the right hand image.
如果我们看一下图片的另一面，我们会看看这个板凳。它非常接近
If we look on the other side of the picture, we look at this bench. It's quite close to
左图中图像的边缘，边缘之间有一点间隙
the edge of the image in the left picture and there is a bit of a gap between the edge
和右手图像中的板凳。这是图像中非常微妙的差异
and the bench in the right hand image. It's this very subtle differences in the image
从这两个观点中可以看出，这些观点为我们提供了非常生动的三维感知
taken from these 2 viewpoints that gives us this very vivid 3-dimensional perception of
我们周围的世界。
the world that's around us.
立体视差的基本原理是图像取决于相机位置
The fundamental principle of stereo disparity is that the image depends on the camera position
我们可以很容易地证明这一点。如果我移动我的头，如果我翻译我的头
and we can demonstrate that pretty easily. If I move my head, if I translate my head
从右到左，世界上的一切似乎都转移到了世界
from the right through to the left then, everything that's in the world appears to move to the
对，但重要的是，像我这样的机器人在我身边的东西似乎在移动
right but importantly, things that are close to me like this robot here, appear to move
在我做这种转变时，图像中有很多。而像书柜那样遥远的东西，
a lot in the image as I do that shift. Whereas things that are far away like the bookcase,
似乎行动少得多。
appear to move much less.
人们一直很想拍摄立体照片很长一段时间。
The people have been interested in capturing stereo photographs for a very very long time.
这是我从1950年代发现的商用立体胶片相机的可爱照片。更多
This is a lovely picture I found of a commercial stereo film camera from the 1950's. A more
现代版的立体相机，这是一种这种类型的数字立体相机
modern version of a stereo camera, this is a digital stereo camera of this type that's
广泛用于机器人系统。
quite widely used for robotic systems.
现在让我们试着了解左手之间究竟有什么区别
Let's now try and understand what precisely are the differences between the left hand
图像和同一场景的右手图像。这是一对高分辨率的数码相机
image and the right hand image of the same scene. This is a pair of high-resolution digital
一堆岩石的图像。
images of a pile of rocks.
我要从图像的左边画一条线到一个相当独特的线
I'm going to draw a line from the left hand edge of the image to a fairly distinctive
在其中一块岩石上划线，我将在右手绘制相同的长度线
blotch on one of the rocks and I'm going to draw the same length line in the right hand
图片。黄线已经走得太远，事实上，我们需要回去
image. The yellow line has gone too far to the right and in fact, we need to go back
为了达到岩石上这个独特标志的距离。
the distance in order to get to this distinctive mark on the rock.
让我们在这里选择另一个与众不同的特色。所以，我要走了
Let's pick another distinctive feature at the back of the scene here. So, I'm going
从左边缘到其中一个大块的边缘画一条黄线
to draw a yellow line from the left hand edge to the edge of one of the large blocks at
背部。我在右手图像中绘制了相同的线条，我们再次看到它超出了
the back. I draw the same line in the right hand image and again, we see that it's overshot,
相应的点，我需要回到距离，以达到相应的点。
the corresponding point and I need to go back the distance in order to get to that corresponding point.
我们注意到两件重要的事情首先，我们注意到右手图像中的点
We noticed 2 important things. First of all, we noticed that points in the right hand image
这个水平位移被称为向左移动并且这个位移
are shifted somewhat to the left and this shift, this horizontal displacement is referred
差距。我们还注意到，对于远离相机的点，移位较少。
to as disparity. We also note that the shift is less for points that are further away from the camera.
所以，在这里我们有一个立体相机，它正在观察一个物体，一个球，然后是
So, here we have a stereo camera and it's observing an object, a ball and that is at
距离相机的距离为Z.我们指的是立体相机的基线，那就是
distance Z away from the camera. We refer to the base line of the stereo camera, that's
镜头中心与F之间的距离是镜头的焦距。我们
the distance between the centre of the lenses and F is the focal length of the lens. We
假设两个镜头具有相同的焦距。
assume that both lenses have the same focal length.
现在，这是这些数量之间非常简单的关系，也就是差异
Now, this is a very simple relationship between these quantities and that is that the disparity
与焦距和基线除以距离成比例。所以，如果我们知道的话
is proportional to the focal length and base line divided by the distance. So, if we know
焦距，我们知道基线，然后我们知道图像中的差异，我们
the focal length, we know the base line and we know the disparity in the image then, we
可以估计Z.这是机器人立体视觉的基本原理，
could estimate Z. This is the fundamental underlying principle of robotic stereovision,
有时它被称为计算立体声，而且隐含地，它就是我们自己的视觉系统中发生的事情。
sometimes it's called computational stereo and implicitly, it's what happens in our own visual system.